Guide to the Annie Schletter Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Annie Schletter papers
1757-1937
GEN MSS 547
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.97
(3 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, printed ephemera, and photographs related to Annie Schletter and her family. Correspondence consists of letters to Annie Schletter, Pauline Schletter, Percy Schletter, and others, including Adrian Boult and Rosetta Phillips. Letters to Annie Schletter, many brief notes, largely relate to theater in London. Her correspondents include Margot Asquith, Adrian Boult, Ernest Coquelin, F. Paolo Tosti, Oscar Wilde, and Charles Wyndham. Correspondence also includes two letters from Georgina Weldon to Pauline Schletter, one written from Halloway Gaol and another enclosing 12 photographs taken in South Africa. Writings include several manuscript poems addressed to Rosetta Phillips, a typescript poem, "National Rat Week," by Osbert Sitwell, and a typescript essay by Margot Asquith describing a visit to Spain. Printed ephemera includes theater programs for performances at the Reform Club, Savoy Theatre, Windsor Castle, and other venues, as well as an invitation and prayer from "Her Majesty's Jubilee Thanksgiving Service." Photographs include portraits of Anthony Asquith, H. H. Asquith, Margot Asquith, Pamela Lytton, and F. Paolo Tosti.
Schletter, Annie, 1858-1944
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Maggs Brothers, November 2003.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
ANNIE SCHLETTER (1858-1944)
Annie Schletter (1858-1944) was an English actress active in London during World War I. She was the sister of Pauline Schletter (b. 1851), a translator. Percy Schletter (1855-1922), a colonel in The King's Liverpool Regiment, was also related, probably their brother.
Scope and Contents
The Annie Schletter papers consist of correpondence, writings, printed ephemera, and photographs related to Annie Schletter and her family, including Pauline Schletter and Percy Schletter, and span the years 1757-1937. The papers are housed in three boxes (including 1 oversize box) and are organized into four series: Correspondence, Writings of Others, Printed Ephemera, and Photographs.
Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two subseries, Annie Schletter Correspondence and Third Party Correspondence, in folders 1-70. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically.
Annie Schletter correspondents include Margot Asquith; Adrian Boult; John Francis Churchill; Ernest Coquelin; Francesco Paolo Tosti; Alfred Vogt; Genevieve Ward; Oscar Wilde; and Charles Wyndham. The bulk of the letters to Annie Schletter are from others involved in London theatre and include acknowledgements of flowers or congratulations sent by Annie Schletter, notes offering or declining roles in various plays, and discussions of other theatre-related matters.
Third Party Correpondence consists of letters to Pauline Schletter, Percy Schletter, and others, including the conductor Adrian Boult, and Rosetta Phillips, who may have been a cousin to Annie Schletter. Many of the third party letters are to unidentified recipients. Correspondents include Richard Aldington; Anthony Asquith; Claude Clark; William Gladstone; Queen Mary, consort of George V; J. B. Palmer; Margaret Teck; and Georgina Weldon. Georgina Weldon's letters to Pauline Schletter include a letter written while Weldon was imprisoned for libel in Halloway Gaol and a letter including 12 photographs that Weldon took in South Africa. The subseries also includes unidentified letters, letter fragments, miscellaneous envelopes, and calling cards.
Series II, Writings of Others, is arranged alphabetically by author in folders 71-78. The bulk of the series consists of manuscript poetry, including several poems addressed to Rosetta Phillips by H. A. D'Alton, M. A. Gaus, and John Ryan, as well as a typescript of "National Rat Week" by Osbert Sitwell and three unattributed poems. Writings of Others also includes "Spain," a signed typescript by Margot Asquith describing a visit there.
Series III, Printed Ephemera, is arranged chronologically in folders 79-86. The bulk of the series consists of programs for performances at various venues, including the Reform Club, the Savoy Theatre, and Windsor Castle, as well as a prayer and invitation from "Her Majesty's Jubilee Thanksgiving Service." Printed ephemera also includes a 1916 almanac, a postcard featuring Herbert Beerbohm Tree, and clippings.
Series IV, Photographs, consists of portraits and is arranged alphabetically by subject in folders 87-92. Portrait subjects include Anthony Asquith, Elizabeth Asquith, H. H. Asquith, Margot Asquith, Henry A. Lytton, Pamela Lytton, and F. Paolo Tosti. Two of the photographs are inscribed to "Anish," probably Annie Schletter, and one is inscribed to Percy Schletter.
Actresses -- Great Britain; Theater -- England -- London; Women in theater -- England; Photographic prints; Theater programs; Asquith, Anthony, 1902-1968; Asquith, H. H. (Herbert Henry), 1852-1928; Asquith, Margot, 1864-1945; Boult, Adrian, 1889-1983; Coquelin, Ernest; Lytton, Pamela; Phillips, Rosetta; Schletter, Annie, 1858-1944; Schletter, Pauline, b. 1851; Schletter, Percy, 1855-1922; Sitwell, Osbert, 1892-1969; Tosti, F. Paolo (Francesco Paolo), 1846-1916; Weldon, Georgina, 1837-1914; Wilde, Oscar, 1854-1900; Wyndham, Charles, 1837-1919
- Correspondence, 1757-1936; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two subseries, Annie Schletter Correspondence and Third Party Correspondence. Both subseries are arranged alphabetically.
  - ANNIE SCHLETTER CORRESPONDENCE
    - Asquith, [Margot], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Series II, Writings of Others, Box 2, folder 71
    - Behnke, Kate Emil, 1913 Nov 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Boult, Adrian, Sir, 1918 Nov 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Braithwaite, Lilian, n.y. Aug 11 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Castle, Agnes Egerton, 1907 Mar 28 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Churchill, John Francis, 1898-1902 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes 2 letters in French. Also includes a pamphlet by Churchill titled Stoechiological Medicine. (London: Merser & Sons, n.d.)
    - Clark, E. Holman, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Clifford, Elizabeth, Lady, 1916 Aug 25 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Cooper, Gladys, 1917 Sep 14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Coquelin, Ernest, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      In French
    - Coquelin, Jean, 1919 Jan 7 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Cottrau, Giulio, 1903 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Crawford, F. Marion, 1902 Mar 19 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - DeFilippi, Filippo, 1918, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Includes a pamphlet, The Geography of the Italian Front (reprinted from The Geographical Journal, Feb 1918), inscribed to Annie Schletter.
    - Fairfax, [Ian?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Filippi, Rosina. Flyer inscribed to Annie [Schletter], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Forbes-Robertson, J., 1907-09, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Haines, Frederick Paul, Sir, 1890 June (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Kendal, Madge (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Linton, E. Lynn (Elizabeth Lynn), 1886 Dec 28 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Milton, Ernest, 1932 Apr 11 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Neilson, Julia, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Neilson-Terry, Phyllis, 1922 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Saintsbury, George, 1889 Feb 21 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Tennant, Gertrude, 1895 Jun 20 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Terry, Marion, 1928 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Tosti, F. Paolo (Francesco Paolo), 1889-98, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
      In Italian
    - Vanbrugh, Irene, 1914 Aug 6 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Vogt, Alfred, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      In German
    - Ward, Genevieve, 1907-19 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Wilde, Oscar, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      In hand of secretary
    - Wyndham, Charles, Sir (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Unidentified correspondents, 1889-1933 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    Each file listed below consists of one letter unless otherwise noted.
    - Aldington, Richard, to unidentified recipient, 1923 Aug 25 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Allen, Hugh Percy, Sir, to Adrian Boult, 1918 Oct 29 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - [Asquith, Anthony], to "Diana," signed "Puffin", 1933 Jul 19 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Boult, Adrian, Sir, to an unidentified recipient, 1918 Aug 6 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Clark, Claude, to Pauline [Schletter], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 38)
      7 letters
    - Davernay, Pauline, to unidentified recipient, 1837 Jul 7 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Deacon, Fred, receipt for 1837 season wages paid to Pauline Davernay, 1837 Aug 23 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Egan, Pierce (1814-1880), to William Brettell, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Eyre, James, Sir, to Brettell, n.y. Apr 27 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Gaus?, M. A., to Rosetta Phillips, n.y. Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Gladstone, W. E. (William Ewert), to unidentified recipient, 1868 Aug 8 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Harrington, Tim, to [Percy Schletter], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 45)
      4 letters
    - Hess, Myra, Dame, to Adrian Boult, 1918 Nov 7 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Lál, Mohan, to Petanus Wray, 1845 Mar 17 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - L. E. L. (Letitia Elizabeth Landon), to Montague (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Linwood, M[ary?], to Mr. Werner, 1825 Jan 23 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Ludwig Salvator, Archduke of Austria, to Percy Schletter, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Mallock, W. H. (William Hurrell), to unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Mary, Queen, consort of George V, King of Great Britain, to unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Melba, Nellie, Dame, to Carmichael, [Thomas David Gibson, Sir, bart.], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Montagu, ----, to unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Palmer, J. B., to Rosetta Phillips, 1842-56 (Box 1, Folder 55)
      6 letters
    - Redfern, Joan, to unidentified recipient, 1931 Feb 9 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Rodrigues, A., Portuguese commissioner of war, to Captain Johnson, 1831 Aug 2 (Box 1, Folder 57)
      In Portuguese
    - Salessy, P., to Bastogi, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 58)
      In Spanish
    - Teck, Margaret, Lady, to Percy Schletter, 1916 Aug (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Thalberg, S[igismond], to unidentified recipient (Box 1, Folder 60)
      Copy. In French
    - Tree, Maud, to unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Varnbery, A., to the editor of the National Review, 1884 Oct 21 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Viel, E., to unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Weldon, Georgina, to [Pauline] Schletter, 1885, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 64)
      2 letters. Includes 12 photographs of South Africa
    - Weldon, Georgina, to le Marquis de Rochefort de Lucay, 1885 May 19
      Printed letter. In French
    - Yate, Charles Edward, to [Percy] Schletter, 1920 Mar 13 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Unidentified
      - Unidentified correspondents to Mr. Brettell (Box 1, Folder 66)
      - Other unidentified letters, 1757, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Letter fragments, 1785-1889, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Envelopes, 1837, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Calling cards, 1837, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 70)
- Writings of Others, 1832-1937; Series II; 8
  Series II, Writings of Others, is arranged alphabetically.
  - Asquith, Margot. "Spain," typescript, signed, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - D'Alton, H. A. (Herbert Andrew). "The Harp," poem, holograph, signed, addressed to Rosetta Phillips, 1832 Mar 26 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Gaus?, M. A. "To My Sister Rosetta" Poem, 2 holograph copies, signed, 1840 Jan 7 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Ryan, John. 3 poems, holograph, signed, addressed to Rosetta Phillips, 1832 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Sitwell, Osbert. "National Rat Week," poem, typescript, 1937 Feb (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Unidentified authors
    - "Desiderio guidicioso," poem, manuscript, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - "The Harp stands neglected its mistress is gone," poem, manuscript (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - "Parody on Moore's There's a Bower of Roses by Bendemeers Stream," poem, manuscript (Box 2, Folder 78)
- Printed Ephemera, 1838-1916; Series III; 8
  Series III, Printed Ephemera, is arranged chronologically.
  - Reform Club program, 1838 Jun 28 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Savoy Theatre programs, 1886-1901 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Her Majesty's Jubilee Thanksgiving Service, prayer and invitation for Percy Schletter, 1887 Jun 21 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Theatre programs, 1895-1909 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Windsor Castle theatrical performance program, menu, and admission card for Annie Schletter, 1914 Feb 2 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    Performance by Mr. Frank Curzon and Mr. Gerald du Maurier's Company
  - "Flanders" Almanac, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    Illustration on cover, "XXth 'Light' Division"
  - Postcard of Herbert Beerbohm Tree, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 85)
    Advertisement for performances of His Majesty's Theatre Company
  - Clippings, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 86)
- Photographs, 1884-1914; Series IV; 7
  Series IV, Photographs, is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Asquith, Anthony. Portrait taken by Will Cadby, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    Inscribed "To Anish"
  - Asquith, Elizabeth. Photograph of a portrait, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    Inscribed "To Anish" and signed by Elizabeth Asquith, 1911.
  - Asquith, H. H. (Herbert Henry). Signed portrait taken by Thomson, n.d.
  - Asquith, Margot. Signed portrait taken by Thomson, n.d.
  - Lytton, Henry A. Signed photomechanical print of Lytton "In 'Patience'", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - "Pamela Lytton 91- Baby Kuchworth", 1914 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - South Africa. 12 photographs taken by Georgina Weldon, 1902
    See: Correspondence, Box 1, folder 64
  - Tosti, F. Paolo (Francesco Paolo). Portrait, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    Inscribed to Percy Schletter
- Oversize, 3; (1 box)
  - Weldon, Georginia, to le Marquis de Rochefort de Lucay (Series I), 1885 May 19 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Asquith, H. H. (Herbert Henry). Signed portrait taken by Thomson (Series IV), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Asquith, Margot. Signed portrait taken by Thomson (Series IV), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 95)